Guide to the American Political Items Collectors collection, 1895-1988
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
American Political Items Collectors collection
1895-1988
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives
American Political Items Collectors
6 linear feet (8 boxes)
The American Political Items Collectors Collection (APIC) contains donations of scholarly material that relates to national political campaigns as well as American history dating from 1895 to 1988. This collection is comprised of presidential campaigning materials that stem from bumper stickers to voting ballots. Not only is it an extensive collection of presidential campaigns but it also houses historical magazines, newspapers, and many other manuscripts and books.
C0023
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Richard Lyon and Robert Fratkin of APIC in 1981 and donated by Theodore Hake in 1982. Additional photographs donated by Mills Kelly in 2009.
Biographical Information
The American Political Items Collectors (APIC) is a non-profit membership organization that seeks to encourage and support the collection, study and preservation of original materials relating to political campaigns of the United States of America. The APIC was founded in 1945 with the hope of promoting the heritage of the United States through the study of materials that cover political campaigns and the presidency.
Scope and Content
The American Political Items Collectors Collection (APIC) contains donations of scholarly material that relates to national political campaigns as well as American history dating from 1895 to 1988. This collection is comprised of presidential campaigning materials that stem from bumper stickers to voting ballots. Not only is it an extensive collection of presidential campaigns but it also houses historical magazines, newspapers, and many other manuscripts and books. The APIC collection is divided into three series for easy research and use. The three series are: Subject Files, arranged alphabetically; Printed Material, arranged alphabetically; and Oversize Materials, separated into posters and newspapers arranged chronologically.
The first series, Subject Files, ranges from 1895 to 1982. It is composed of campaigning materials from presidential candidates such as Jimmy Carter, Hubert Humphrey,George McGovern, Richard Nixon and many more. Included in this campaigning material are informational pamphlets, stickers and stamps. The inaugural events and invitations to John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson's inaugural celebration are included here as well as a copy of the Watergate Transcript. The historic voting ballots of 1936 which elected Franklin D. Roosevelt president are in this collection as well. Also in the Subject Files is a collection of magazines such as "Time" and "Life" from 1960-1967 that cover the life and death of President John F. Kennedy. Lyndon B. Johnson's photography book entitled "This America" is also included here.
The second series, Printed Material, is composed of magazines, newsletters and books dating from 1932 to 1982. Included in this collection is the APIC newsletter, "Keynoter," dating from 1967 to 1982, as well as the 1965 APIC "Brummagem." Also included are special 1976 magazine issues covering the 200-year anniversary of America. Magazines included for these special anniversary issues are "McCall's," "Time," and "Newsweek." Also provided in the Printed Materials series are handbooks, pamphlets, admission tickets and official proceeding booklets of the Democratic National Convention from the years 1964 to 1976. Other printed material included in this collection are copies of "Political Intelligence" newsletter, "The Capitol," and "The Standard."
The third series in the APIC collection, Oversize Material, is composed of posters, newspapers, photographs, political buttons and a Presidential Fact Finder Wheel artifact. Posters date from as early as 1940 up to as late as 1980. Some highlights in the poster collection include posters of Ronald Reagan and George Bush, Jimmy Carter and Walter Mondale, Richard Nixon, Andrew Pulley and Matilde Zimmerman of the Socialist Workers Party, and Henry Wallace. The newspaper collection contains articles from 1961 to 1981 and is composed of the "Washington Post," "Washington Star," "Washington Daily News," and the "New York Times." Important subjects of these newspapers range from President John F. Kennedy's assassination and internment as well as the marriage of Chuck Robb and Lynda Bird Johnson. Other highlights are the 100 year anniversary of the Battle of Gettysburg and the inauguration coverage of Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan. There are also three large format photographs from the 1988 Democratic National Convention and the 1988 Republican National Convention. The photographs are of Michael Dukakis' acceptance speech, Beryl Ann Bentson, Lloyd Bentson, Michael Dukakis, and Kitty Dukakis together on the stage, Senator Paul Simon speaking to reporters, Jesse Jackson, Pat Robertson, and Jerry Falwell. The three political buttons feature "Vote Communist for a free, happy, prosperous America", "Ollie for President!", and "Bush, Quayle '88".
Arrangement
Organized into three series:
Series 1: Subject Files, 1895-1982 (Boxes 1-3)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1932-1982 (Boxes 3-6)
Series 3: Oversize Material, 1940-1988 (Boxes 7-8)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds collections of many Northern Virginia local and national political leaders and organizations, such as the, the William L. Scott Papers, and the.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Political campaigns--United States.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.
Persons:
Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.
Contents List
- Series 1: Subject Files 1895-1982, 2.5 Boxes
  The first series, Subject Files, ranges from 1895 to 1982. It is composed of campaigning materials from presidential candidates such as Jimmy Carter, Hubert Humphrey,George McGovern, Richard Nixon and many more. Included in this campaigning material are informational pamphlets, stickers and stamps.
  - APIC Meeting, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barry, Marion, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coxey, J.S., 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goldwater, Barry, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. ("Time," "Life"), 1964-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. ("This America"), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kennedy, John F. ("Time," "Look"), 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kennedy, John F. ("Life"), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kennedy, John F. ("Life"), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kennedy, Robert, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - McGovern, George, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1936, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E., 1952, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Watergate Transcript, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Printed Material, 1897-1982, 3.5 Boxes
  The second series, Printed Material, is composed of magazines, newsletters and books dating from 1932 to 1982.
  - Anniversary Magazine Issues ("McCalls," "Time," "Newsweek"), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "APIC Brummagem", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "APIC Keynoter, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "APIC Keynoter", 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "APIC Newsletter", 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - APIC Research Project, "Parker and Davis", 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "APIC Roster", 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Auction Catalogs, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Civil Rights, "The People Take the Lead", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Democratic Convention, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - National Democratic Convention, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Democratic and Republican Platforms (PA), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Democratic Review", 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Federal Election Campaign Laws", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Financial Management System for Political Campaigns", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Look Out Neighbor", 1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Platforms of the Two Great Political Parties", 1932-1948 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Political Intelligence" newsletter, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Presidential Campaign in Buttons", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "The Presidents of the United States", 1897-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Project '68 and '76", 1968,1976 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "The Capitol", 1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "The Standard", 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series 3: Oversize Material, 1940-1988, 2 Boxes
  The third series in the APIC collection, Oversize Material, is composed of posters, newspapers, photographs, and political buttons. Posters date from as early as 1940 up to as late as 1980.
  - Ronald Reagan, George Bush poster, 1980 (Oversize 7, Folder 1)
  - Ronald Reagan, George Bush poster, 1980 (Oversize 7, Folder 2)
  - Andrew Pulley, Socialist Workers Party, Presidential candidate, poster, 1980 (Oversize 7, Folder 3)
  - Matilde Zimmerman, Socialist Workers Party, V.P. candidate, poster, 1980 (Oversize 7, Folder 4)
  - Edward Clark, poster, 1980 (Oversize 7, Folder 5)
  - Jimmy Carter and Walter Mondale, poster, 1976 (Oversize 7, Folder 6)
  - George Wallace, poster, 1974 (Oversize 7, Folder 7)
  - Richard Nixon, poster, 1972 (Oversize 7, Folder 8)
  - George McGovern and Sgt. Shriver, poster, 1972 (Oversize 7, Folder 9)
  - George Schmitz and Thomas J. Anderson, poster, 1972 (Oversize 7, Folder 10)
  - George Wallace, 1972 (Oversize 7, Folder 11)
  - George Wallace, Undated (Oversize 7, Folder 12)
  - Henry Wallace, 1940 (Oversize 7, Folder 13)
  - Kennedy Inaugural Edition, "Washington Evening Star," newspaper, January 20, 1961 (Oversize 8, Folder 1)
  - Kennedy is Killed, "Washington Daily News," newspaper, November 22, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 2)
  - Kennedy is Killed, "Washington Evening Star," newspaper, November 22, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 3)
  - Kennedy Lies in State, "New York Times," newspaper, November 24, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 4)
  - Kennedy Lies in State, "Washington Post," newspaper, November 24, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 5)
  - Kennedy Tribute, "Washington Daily News," newspaper, November 25, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 6)
  - Oswald is Shot, "Washington Post," newspaper, November 25, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 7)
  - Nation Buries President, "Washington Post," newspaper, November 26, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 8)
  - 100th Anniversary of Battle of Gettysburg, "Gettysburg Times," newspaper, 1963 (Oversize 8, Folder 9)
  - Convention and Election Almanac, "Washington Post," newspaper, August 23, 1964 (Oversize 8, Folder 10)
  - Chuck Robb and Lynda Bird Johnson Marry, "Washington Post," newspaper, December 10, 1967 (Oversize 8, Folder 11)
  - Chuck Robb and Lynda Bird Johnson Marry, "Washington Star," newspaper, December 10, 1967 (Oversize 8, Folder 12)
  - Nixon Sworn In, "Washington Post," newspaper, January 20, 1969 (Oversize 8, Folder 13)
  - Jimmy Carter Inaugural, "Washington Star," newspaper, January 20, 1977 (Oversize 8, Folder 14)
  - Jimmy Carter Inaugural, "Washington Star," newspaper, January 20, 1977 (Oversize 8, Folder 15)
  - Humphrey Dies, "Washington Star," newspaper, January 14, 1978 (Oversize 8, Folder 16)
  - Humphrey Dies, "Washington Post," newspaper, January 14, 1978 (Oversize 8, Folder 17)
  - Humphrey Lies in State, "Washington Star," newspaper, January 15, 1978 (Oversize 8, Folder 18)
  - Humphrey Lies in State, "Washington Post," newspaper, January 15, 1978 (Oversize 8, Folder 19)
  - Inauguration '81, The Reagan Presidency, "Washington Post," newspaper, January 20, 1981 (Oversize 8, Folder 20)
  - Inauguration '81, Inaugural Address, newspaper, January 21, 1981 (Oversize 8, Folder 21)
  - Democratic and Republican National Convention Photographs, 1988 (Oversize 8, Folder 22)
  - Political buttons, undated-1988, Three buttons (Oversize 8, Folder 23)